From time to time I I I'm reminded of
the story by Ajahn Chah that
you know, he had his ways of teaching
the the agents and then Westerners came.
And after a while he he he
started treating them differently
because he he realized the difference
the background, right? So so so he as
Ajahn Chah
explained in the book, he was like this
um
kind father figure something like that
because he figured out that they were
going to matching the
in in the other direction.
And um
so so that's the setup and then
you know, we we are living in this
strange kind of not even what these
modernists but what is postmodernists
when when we have like different lot of
different teachings.
And and the advantage of that actually a
lot of advant- disadvantages but one of
the advantages that you can think about
how teachings themselves in a way are
also conditioned and fabricated and and each
conditioned and fabricated and and each
per each each teaching has a different
direction which means it also has its own kind of
which means it also has its own kind of
blind spots in a way.
Um and just
my kind of impression is that and
obviously also which means that some
people may be drawn to some teachings
not for the right reasons but for the
wrong reasons.
Um
so I'm wondering whether
and also like having read some
his side hermitage read it also noticed
some um some
uh some posts where people said were
saying I I I'm keeping the sense
restraint for a long time and still
there's nothing and even Bhante said
I don't I never use this word but you
know, it's more about like being now or
something like he had to you know, kind
of make this correction. So um
so um yeah, I'm just wondering in
general about that because when you
think about this kind of anxiety and
neuroticism you can be immersed with it within it
you can be immersed with it within it
and and and don't notice it and from
that place
keep restraining the sense senses but
what's actually restraining you is this
harshness on yourself, right? Well,
basically yes. I think we spoke about it
yesterday as well a little bit. Um
it's like
keeping the precepts needs to be done
in that
through that personal responsibility.
Like each and every time you restrain
your intentions or desires, the mind
will come up
well with with
with a degree of objection to that.
The mind is not happy that you're
restraining it.
So what do you do then? Do you then just
distract yourself from
the disturbed mind that now you have to
put up with because you said no to your
desires? Or do you know, allow that mind as well
Or do you know, allow that mind as well
and endure that level?
See, I often talk about it but I know
it's kind of it's general audience. Like
if I talk one-on-one with somebody
for hours and I can understand more more
specifically where they're coming from,
you can give more accurate same like
with a doctor, you know, you can give a
general antibiotic cuz you did not give
him any details about your illness, just
describe general symptoms or he can give
you exact thing that you need if he can
boil it down to it.
So most of this stuff it's the general
audience. So it's kind of tailored for
generally I kind of know where people come from
I kind of know where people come from
cuz I was one of such people
and European culture as different as
nationalities are general, it's not the
same. It's it's not too different.
Um people don't want to practice sense
restraint, they don't want to give up
things, they want everything on easier
terms, talking about responsibilities
unpleasant and fills them with anxiety.
Which is exactly all of it that they
need to do.
So yes, somebody if it's too much, you
can tell him in a gentle way but if it's
not then he has to hear it harder.
But the point is you have to recognize
that many people would hear it in this
general manner but still have the same
attitude. They wouldn't really
understand it. So when I talk about
enduring things on the right level,
people think okay, so I just need to
mindlessly bear discomfort until the
magic of sotapatti happens. I never ever
said anything remotely like that. The
the whole book
that I that first one is like this well,
second one
describes the right level in so many
different ways to recognize okay, that's
it's not like you're saying no to
everything until you're
tightly wound that it's just you're
going to burst. No, it's saying no to
things you need to say no to.
Lust, aversion, distraction, delusion,
irritation choice, things that are based on your
choice, things that are based on your
choice that you actively maintain and
do. Weaknesses that you actively in full
Weaknesses that you actively in full
awareness give into.
And now you don't just mindless like
like blindly just okay, I'll just say no
to this and keep the precepts and when
when is it happening?
No, the point of keeping the precepts is
so that your mind comes up in that
feedback that's going to be almost
certainly unpleasant initially.
And then you don't try to get rid of
that. You can get rid of other stuff if you
You can get rid of other stuff if you
want.
Um so it's a bit more nuanced than just
keep the precepts and bear it like a
donkey or something and then everything
will fall into place which just becomes
another method
which I always criticize. Like so even
if the right thing people can take
taking that external method, I just
stick to this mindlessly
without recognizing my responsibility,
my choice, my influence and my refusal
to bear the state of mind on that subtle
level where the doubt is, where the
anxiety is.
As I was saying this morning, you don't
need great pains and great torment to
bring these things up. Just say no to
the the sensual desires that you want,
acting out of anger and stay with what's
left. Not too much, not too little. It's going
Not too much, not too little. It's going
to come up on its own.
And that's the training and that's the
uptaking upholding of the virtue.
Not just sort of technically learning
all the allowables and non-allowables
and then revolving around that to
protect you magically from these mental
states. No, they're supposed to come up
if the virtue is done rightly. So if you
think your virtue is great and you're
keeping the precepts and you're
perfectly restrained and the mind is not
coming up with anything with no
irrational attacks and thoughts and
doubts, you're either fully enlightened
or you're doing it wrong.
You can't be oh, but I'm doing it right
and my mind is just not doing any of
this. It will be coming up with stuff
because you are confining it
which is the precursor to taming it. Right.
Right.
Right because uh
And that's the thing. See, whether it's
a fatherly figure and pat on the back or
a stern advice,
you have to do the same work. There is
no way around that.
Sure, you can present it differently to
different people
depending on the experience of the of
the teacher and how many people you
dealt with but more likely than not
today for whoever wants to do it, it will be
for whoever wants to do it, it will be
unpleasant to begin with.
Because you will on average you won't
find a person that's thoroughly
established in self-control that hasn't
been controlled by their own desires for
years that hasn't been giving into it
mindlessly because he was never told not
to.
So it will take time to undo that.
Have it that addiction and that that
can't possibly be It doesn't mean it
will be terribly unpleasant. It depends
on the person and the strength of their
um underlying tendencies but it's the
same it's the same work.
And often when I hear people say like
you know, it would be helpful
that like you know, such advice is put
in such manner. It's like you don't know
that. It's just a preference. It would
be maybe less painful to hear it that
way but it doesn't mean it would be
helpful for you.
Cuz if you're already concerned about
whether this will be painful for me to
hear it or not you're going to be even
more concerned when that pain actually
comes when it comes to sense restraint
and stuff. So
yeah.
a follow-up question
cuz I I'm not sure I understood the
difference from what
like after Amida's question, I think you
even started with like somebody
like
holding the precepts kind of like with
brute force Blindly, yeah. Waiting for
some magic to happen.
And now
you were saying
that if you start doing it, there will
be some unpleasantness.
Uh so it sounds a bit like there will be
some unpleasantness but
then what you do?
what you do?
Like but but at some point there will be
no unpleasantness or Yeah, it's true.
Eventually if there is no more pull towards things
if there is no more pull towards things
you said no to
there will be no discomfort.
Like if you don't want to go to
Well, you don't want to go to Slovenia
now. You don't want to go to Slovenia
and I tell you you can't go to Slovenia
today. Would you be upset cuz you don't
even want to go there. You you wouldn't
care less. You'd be like, well, fine.
But if you really want to go to
Slovenia, I say no, you can't go. Then
you're going to be you're going to feel
that. But the
But the
because it sounds kind of like you
you hold the precepts and wait for magic
to happen.
Well, no, that's that's my thing. The
magic is the pain.
So if you take magic to be the pain,
sure. Go for that magic but that's not the
Go for that magic but that's not the
magic, isn't it?
Magic is I hold the precepts so this
will stop coming up magically.
No, I hold the precepts and this comes
up and I don't complain about it.
And I don't give into it. And I don't
try to get rid of it.
I allow it to be there
so that I can train in regard to it.
Because if I want to deal with it
immediately, I'm just acting out of aversion towards
I'm just acting out of aversion towards
pain, which is one of the roots of
suffering, craving against discomfort.
So yes, you need to know the precepts.
Yes, they're the technical aspects of
it. So if I may Uh-huh. So the
difference would be instead of just kind
of forcefully holding to precepts and
waiting for magic to happen, it's kind
of
starting to be at comfort with
discomfort. Well, let's see. Like even that, the way
Well, let's see. Like even that, the way
you presented is so that you won't feel
discomfort. Well, I need to learn how to be
Well, I need to learn how to be
comfortable with discomfort so that I
don't feel discomfort.
And that's intention, it's already
rooted it. I refuse to accept
confinement of discomfort.
So I will do anything I can to get rid
of it.
So it's more about what you want to do.
Let's put it that way.
You keep the precepts.
The pain comes up. The mind is re-
rejecting the idea of precepts.
And you don't know what to do.
You're full of doubt. You're full of
anxiety. You're full of pressure.
I told you that meditation techniques
are management. They will probably take
you further away in the wrong view. So
you don't do that. You don't So what do
I do?
And it's a absolute despair, panic,
confinement. But you still know what not to do.
But you still know what not to do.
You don't break the precepts. You don't
lose the senses strength. That's what
you do.
That's what when they asked the Buddha,
"How did you" says the Buddha says, "If
you swim too hard crossing the crossing
the river,
you tie yourself against the waves and
you sink.
If you swim too feebly, the waves the
the the current just sweeps you away. If
you try and stand still, you sink.
So what did Master Gotama do then to
cross the river? He says, "Well, I
didn't swim too hard, nor did I swim
backwards, nor did I stay still."
He didn't say, "Oh, I did this fourth
thing in between." No, I did not doing
of these certain things, and that's that
was his practice.
And that's a lot subtler and a lot
harder to accept because see, now you
have to live with that doubt.
Which is like one of the it's quite an
unpleasant hindrance, probably more than
others as well.
Because it it it comes from your core.
Yeah, but and that's why again, like
when when it comes to these meditation
techniques or methods or just the whole
attitude to have something more clearly,
just tell me what to do that I can stick
to. That's why. Because this is way too
That's why. Because this is way too
uncomfortable.
But as I was describing this morning,
ask yourself, "Hold on, but why is this
Why is this, which is factually not the
most painful thing, there are lots more
painful thing you can imagine going
through, but why is this the worst one? Why is
but why is this the worst one? Why is
this that nobody wants to do?
Like it would be easier if you just hit
me with a rod 100 times than having to
spend a week in a solitary confinement
with a mind infected with doubt.
That's like I'll go mad.
So it's the hardest is just to live with
yourself. While everything else
factually harder, it's not as bad.
And that should certainly be a a good
reason and incentive to reflect on this
because it doesn't add up, doesn't it?
it doesn't add up, doesn't it?
Seemingly, you are your own man in in
control of your choices and everything
else. Yet being with yourself is the
worst thing the mind resists it the
most. And I mean, people did loads of far
And I mean, people did loads of far
worse stuff and self-torment and the
even the suttas describe it, just to not
have to endure it on this mental level.
So instead of having this mind of doubt
nagging me for 5 days, I can't sleep at
night, I'll go and I'll I'll walk 300 km and
I'll go and I'll I'll walk 300 km and
live only on water and show my great
resolve and determination and literally
bring yourself to the brink of death.
That's easier than just staying with
this mind and not trying to get rid of
it. But not breaking the precepts on account
But not breaking the precepts on account
of it either.
Isn't the worst punishment in prison?
Yeah. Solitary confinement. Yeah, that's
what I was giving an example in the
morning. You got people that just All
they know in their life is pain.
Inflicted and they enjoy it basically.
There's nothing can scare them. Nothing
can You put them in a solitary
confinement and within a week, they cry
like little children. They can't handle
it. It's just too much mentally. Their
own thoughts.
That's because that that that the the
animal, the mind,
has been allowed to run wild for so
long. And now when you're left with it, well,
And now when you're left with it, well,
you are you you become aware that you
were the victim of it. Yeah, you have no
distractions. No one to get angry at.
Right? But yourself. Yeah, all of those
outlets would exactly be that, just
taking it away from you where you deep
down you know where the problem is.
That's what I said. Everybody deep down
wants peace, even people that say, "No,
no, no, I enjoy busy life and sensuality
and everything is caused for them
through their view, that's where the
peace will be implied at least or come
from at the end of it.
That's the fundamental offer of
sensuality, satisfaction, contentment,
peace.
Every single time.
And then you realize, "Hold on, but
if I need to keep it in moving this,
that's not peaceful.
That's more of a trap.
So like to give you another practical
example in terms of the precept, say you
take a precept to not eat afternoon.
It's like I won't eat past 12. It
doesn't actually say 12. This is noon.
Why was the noon? Well, when the sun is
the highest.
Which could be, you know, half an hour
this way, half an hour that way. But
today we have clocks, so let's say 12.
We can do 12.
And then you couldn't eat in time.
And then it was 12:15.
And now do you eat or not?
Well, what would you do? I would eat.
You would eat. And then?
And then I would try next day to be in
time. To be in time. But what if you fail next
To be in time. But what if you fail next
day?
Does that mean you're not keeping that
precept anymore?
Cuz you ate 15 minutes late?
I think
if
it becomes a habit, then yes.
But 12:15
becomes a habit of 12:15. Why is that a
problem? Why the 15 minutes on the
clock? I would say then I'm a person who is
I would say then I'm a person who is
15 minutes after noon. After the noon,
but the noon was never directly
astronomically specified. Yes. But more
more or less, roughly. Yeah, but why is
it a problem? That's my question.
Like I'm not I'm not sure if it's a
problem. It depends on what was why I
wanted to do this in the Well, exactly.
So
you wouldn't you shouldn't you won't if
you start doing it rightly.
These technicalities, so to speak,
will stay just that.
And if you ate and see, one day you can
eat at quarter to 12
and be within your precept and do it for
completely unwholesome reasons.
Because the criteria
for precepts, if they're done rightly,
is on the internal side every single
time. It's not on 12:00 and ding dong, you can
It's not on 12:00 and ding dong, you can
have it now or you can't. It's why am I
doing this? Am I eating for the right
reasons? Oh, I keep the precepts. I
always eat before 12. Therefore, I don't
have to think why I eat.
That's goes back onto that mindless
keeping the precept of "Oh well, my duty
is fulfilled."
No, your duty starts with the precepts.
Your practice begins if obviously you
look in the right direction.
So if you then say one day you eat at
12:30 and then you start feeling guilty
and remorseful and feel like you broke
all the precepts
cuz you you you broke the letter of the
rule for 15 minutes.
What do you do then? What would you do
then? Say, I'll give you an example it
happens to you and you have this mind of
doubt now
and feel unpleasant and guilty
cuz you ate and you were not clear why
you ate.
You were careless.
Like my my approach would be to
investigate why was I trying to do this
in the first place. Which one? Eating?
Yes, I think. But it already happened.
It doesn't really matter now, isn't it?
You It happens. You ate. Like you were
remorseful. If I know what is the goal
with it, I I may be wrong with being
remorseful. Uh like
Uh like
Well, see, that's the point.
The remorse is there. Whether it's right
or wrong, doesn't matter.
But it will go away. And if if I
understand what is going on, then maybe
it just won't appear in the future.
Exactly. So you want to prevent remorse
from arising.
You want to prevent guilt from arising.
Cuz you don't want to have it there.
And that's the problem.
It wasn't the guilt to begin with.
That's why I talk about
psychologizations of you. Why
investigate what All of that or I'll
focus and I'll do this and I'll just so
that this never comes up again.
Cuz it's unpleasant.
And that's actually what you need to
investigate. Why by default
Why by default
I lean with my entire being against
discomfort. Against the mental pain.
Against the mental pain.
Like in this way you could do anything
against the precepts, for example.
No. No, you can't. Because you start
with the precepts.
You with knowing what you shouldn't be
with knowing what you shouldn't be
doing. But see, that's why I gave you
the example. And And that's exactly what
the mind also So I can go and kill them.
You can't. You know that.
But if the precept says
finish eating by noon and noon is not
specified and you feel guilty on account
of non-specificity cuz your mind is
infected with doubt, and instead of
allowing that doubt to fully arise, even
if it threatens to overwhelm you, you
want to cut it up and create more
precepts and more rules and more modes
of behavior so that this doesn't come
up. In other words, so that the practice
doesn't come up because that's what the
practice is.
And that's exactly why the mind would
want to throw you the other way
completely. Oh, look, 50 minutes late,
you might as well go and get a wife.
It's It's all the same, isn't it? It's
That's what I mean. It will be throwing
irrational things at you to get you to
stop keeping the precepts.
So, what what is the practice then? The
practice then is to learn the precepts
and keep them.
But when anything within the precepts,
when anything when an unwholesome
hindrance comes up, do not start to aim
at the more precepts and more of this
and and finding why did this happen 3
days ago, but instead recognize that
there and then discomfort that came up
is the result of rightly keeping the
precepts. And don't try to get rid of it. Don't
And don't try to get rid of it. Don't
try to distract yourself from it. That's
the enduring on the right level. You can
live in the utmost comfort if you want.
But this is the level I talk about that
things should be endured at.
The tapas that the Buddha talks about,
the purification, it's not like through
water washing and whatnot. It's having
these mental states there
and become familiar with them without
immediately panicking and trying to
resolve them.
Cuz doubt, what's what's the Why is Why
is doubt a problem?
There are loads of things that you don't
know. Loads of things you're doubtful.
But only sometimes it's a problem.
Only sometimes comes with a pressure
that you want to resolve it, get rid of it,
you want to resolve it, get rid of it,
or whatever, manage it away.
Why is that?
It's obviously not because what you
don't know because as I said, there are
millions of other things you don't know.
It's because at that time, for whatever
reason, it's felt painfully.
So, although it presents itself like,
"Oh, I'm doubtful about this. If I find
more information and reasons why, if I
include more data about this,
I will resolve it." But it was never
about the data or the lack of it. It was
about doing anything and everything to
remove the pain.
And once you recognize that content of
the doubt is irrelevant,
it's the attitude towards the discomfort
of it that's what matters.
You stop resisting it, and then you stop
following the doubt, and that's how you
go beyond it.
Sotapanna goes beyond doubt not because
he learned everything about everything
in this world, it's because his mind
seen through it and cannot be moved by
the presence of the discomfort of the
doubt.
Cannot make him act
like he did before.
But the doubt appears to a sotapanna.
One It It It would in regard to things,
in regard to lack of knowledge, in
regard to lack of clarity. Doesn't act
out of it. Yes.
It won't be It won't be causing It won't
be coming out of that pressure. See, cuz
as I said, it tricks you.
It wants you to act out, to get
information, to resolve, to make sure
this is never done again, and all of
those kind of grandiose outpourings only
because you don't want the pain of it.
Yeah, sotapanna cannot resist the
discomfort of it. That's what he has
trained his mind to do.
And thus there will be no pain that
comes as a result of that resistance.
And then you have no problem if it comes
up 100 more times.
Nor will your confidence diminish
because you know it's always just going
to be the same thing.
But if you're aiming at removing the
content of the doubt,
you are doing so with the implication of
hopefully it will never come back again.
I resolved it finally, once and for all.
And then 5 minutes later again.
And again.
And you get irrational loop.
Cuz as I said, you're addressing it
where it isn't
the problem.
So, you're closer to address the doubt
for good
by allowing it to arise,
not acting out of it on that mental
level, than to like learn everything
that wants to direct you towards.
And that's why you did have people in
the suttas that fully purified their
mind on the time of mere faith in the basic
on the time of mere faith in the basic
instruction that the Buddha gave. There
was no moving parts, no 150 suttas, any
information. It was just anything
mentally unwholesome,
don't cultivate it, don't give in to it,
don't don't try to get rid of it.
And if stuff is not unwholesome, leave
it, no problem, but don't lose the sight
of it.
And that was enough for them to do all
the work where it matters.
But you still resolved to do
the strength
like not
So, it's not the fear of
of remorse for the next day going with
the example of Vikalabhojana, Uh-huh.
So, today it But why why do you Why would
today it But why why do you Why would
you resolve to do differently if it's
if it's not really against the precepts
or if it's not that clear? So, it's Like
it doesn't make a difference whether
it's 12:00 or 12:15 factually.
Cuz it's not specified. Yet it's easier
if it's 12:00, isn't it? No.
Yeah, so but it doesn't make a
difference. So, why do you feel like
you're not keeping the precepts if you
eat at 12:15? But you feel
but that's today, I don't want to feel
bad tomorrow. Yeah, but see, that that
type of pain
And If you don't want it, you don't want
the right level where the practice is.
So, if you try to prevent, "Oh, I will
do this so that this doesn't come up."
What you're saying is, "I'll do random
external things so that I don't have to
deal with my mind. I'll pacify it. I'll
prevent it from going there and so on."
You already did that. By taking on the
precepts, you have created a boundary
that's quite clear.
Killing, stealing, cheating, lying,
if they get precepts,
eating at the wrong time, and all of
that. But these are like 15 minutes.
It's not They didn't have clocks. They
didn't have time.
Monks used to go pindapat at night
and eat multiple times a day.
It was not a problem.
said not to. Yeah, but not because it
was relevant for the Dhamma, it's
because they were following it
Again, a circumstantial thing. The
Buddha also did say to the monks on his
deathbed, "You can abandon all the
circumstantial rules. I allow you to."
Uh-huh. Fault
Fault
wouldn't be in that 15 minutes break,
but in giving in to that Yeah. pain
That's what I'm I'm not so sure I I'm
grasping. Well, yeah, cuz if you start grasping
Well, yeah, cuz if you start grasping
it, you probably won't need my talks
anyway. Okay. That I heard. And that's
the point. And you will start grasping
it not by Well, you should try and and
attempt to understand it. But you have
to start doing it. You have to start
allowing that particular level where the
doubt is, where the little anxieties
are, to arise and not to feel fully justified
to arise and not to feel fully justified
that, "Okay, where is my Dhamma to to to
deal with this?"
There is no management when it comes
a different one also from Punnisa.
You said for you it was also it was very
easy to quit alcohol. For me it wasn't.
So, when I came to Poland with eight
precepts and my family, it was COVID
time and my family was drinking a lot
uh
to ease the pain or the boredom or or
the anxiety of COVID and lockdowns. And
I'm not saying they're alcoholics.
But Mhm.
they were drinking.
And so because I used to drink normally,
uh when I
was under precepts, I could
completely see the anxiety and how
people were getting drunk and they were
getting They were asking me more
They were asking me more
personal questions and they were getting
braver with their attitude towards me.
And I was also getting stronger, but I
was mhm I had some So, I had panic, but
I also had joy. Mhm. Mhm.
As as as emotions as far as emotions go.
So, I did
I did
So, let's say I didn't have a drink. So,
I didn't
you know, I didn't have the late meal to
be remorseful of.
But I had a lot of joy even though it
was painful, even though it was, you
know, not easy to get used to
uh be around people that do drink Yeah.
uh without me drinking. So, is
So, is there anything wrong with the joy
as well? So, I resolved not to drink No.
because it brings me You know, there's
nothing wrong with You know, because it
feels good. Yeah. Even though it feels
not so good in the beginning. There's no
problem with the joy, but I'm pretty
sure you're going to have other precepts
or other examples where non-joy will
come up, where hindrances will come up.
Absolutely. No, no. So, that's where you
look. Yeah, you don't have to Oh, joy is
bad. Not at all. So, if
But if I eat on time and it brings me
joy, Well, again, that wasn't the question I
Well, again, that wasn't the question I
started with. I started what if you
don't eat at the time, would that bring
you sadness?
I know. Yes.
If it brings you joy when you eat on
time, great. But if it brings you
sadness if you don't eat on time, well,
is that also great?
Would it be worse then to skip the meal
and feel hungry?
You tell me. You tell me. Why would you
skip the meal? I would skip it. Why?
Cuz that's just how my mind So, you
don't feel remorseful on something that
wasn't even defined.
hunger and I deal with it and I No, no,
no. Hold that second now. You'll be
dealing with hunger and all this because
you don't want to deal with remorse that
you know is irrational.
But see, it's irrational remorse. You
should be remorseful if there is no
question about alcohol, you can't drink,
and then you drink it, and then you're
remorseful. Yeah.
And it is a problem. And don't drink it
again. That's why I said, you already
know the precepts. Mhm. But the whole
point of the precepts is
when it comes to this actual training,
you have stuff that you just give up.
Alcohol, cheating, lying, killing. Yeah.
But speech precepts that are all those
modifications, the four types, and
eating and sleeping, that's not like
it's not immoral. Okay, I understand
that. the That's where the precepts
the That's where the precepts
change into the training. Yeah. So see,
you would be not training
but refusing the irrational remorse on
account of something that you know it's
not the precepts. It's against what I
decided 12:00, but it's not against the
precepts. Because see, it's easy easier
Because see, it's easy easier
when you build up a determination and
have it set on paper
or have the tradition or environment
force it on you. Then I don't have to
feel this doubt, the ambiguity, the pressure
this doubt, the ambiguity, the pressure
every single time these desire come up.
And that means you won't be training.
That's Silabbata-paramasa. The first
fetter is the fetter It's like people
often translate that Let me just just
finish this. People often translate that
saying Silabbata-paramasa it's it's
believing in rites and ritual. No, it's
Sila, the same word. Bata, duty.
Paramasa fettering you. Sense of duty
to keep this Sila in that external
manner. That's what's preventing you from
That's what's preventing you from
practicing rightly.
Dhamma and Vinaya was always taught
together, not separate. There was no
separate thing.
And that's why like it's so the
the first stage of enlightenment is the
person is referred to established in
virtue. I the precepts became this
training, became this mental level that
I'm talking about where now you know
that's where the Dhamma is. And that's
why you don't need any more input or any
other guidance. You you know exactly
where it is and you know exactly what
needs to be purified. But whether you
choose to do it or not, that's a
different matter, but it becomes clear.
Yeah. And then you can't hold the precepts in
And then you can't hold the precepts in
this external manner even if you want
to. What are you going to say? Uh I wanted
What are you going to say? Uh I wanted
to refer to this joy she talked about
Isn't it possible that the joy
uh can be
like proud like I'm better than Exactly.
You can't You have to see what it is.
It's not going to be It's always going
to be like this type of joy. It can be a
genuine joy Oh, I'm so glad I don't have
to deal with all these emotional ups and
downs cuz I don't drink.
Or it can be Yeah, I'm better than all
of these. I've seen both in people.
I've seen both. Like I'm so pure I don't
I'm better than all of you because all
of these little things that I do.
is so tricky cuz sometimes you're just
content with your behavior and just like
few millimeters further you become being
like proud Well, see that's not the
problem though. As we spoke this morning
Um
Oh, with with you and you, yeah. The
mind will come up. The mind will
overstep. But you don't go back to drinking or you
But you don't go back to drinking or you
don't act out of it.
You can't stop the mind thinking it's
own.
Exactly. So you don't act out of it.
That's my point. You don't You don't
drink and then you start being proud and
then you go, "Okay, that's now the level
created by my restraint and I shouldn't
be acting out of that now."
I should not lose the sight of it and
start acting and saying things and doing
things that come from this place. Yeah,
but for me it's easier to prevent
acting, but it's harder to prevent the
emotions and opinions and You can't
prevent that. That's the whole point.
Acting is within your choice. That's the
the gate you open for the wild dog.
Emotions responsible about these things
that Well, you are responsible by not
taming the dog. You're not responsible
for what dog thinks at the time, but
people will blame you cuz it's your dog.
So you are responsible by not taming it.
But people say, "I'm not responsible."
means what? I need to kill the dog so he
stops thinking these things. Well, no,
you're still going to be responsible for
killing the dog then. And I shouldn't be
upset about the dog's thoughts.
It depends. What are the thoughts?
But see, you're not upset about the
dog's thoughts. You're upset that the
dog's thoughts are bothering you and you
don't want that.
So you're trying to prevent them from
coming up.
That's not the responsibility of yours.
Your responsibility is to not try to
deny them or give in to them.
Cuz as I said, you want to tame the dog.
Not kill it or let it loose.
Strangle it so it doesn't think anymore
or let it go away.
and the dog doesn't want to. Exactly. So
you need to learn how to communicate
with it. And that's this whole
approach of
recognizing where you do have a say
and then not irrationally resisting the
discomfort of emotions
doubts, opinions that come from the dog.
They want to push you to start acting
where you do have a say.
That's that right level that's going to
be uncomfortable uncomfortable.
push me to feel guilty, not even act,
but There you go. Now the guilt is something
There you go. Now the guilt is something
you have to put endure until it's there
on that mental level. But you still know
what not to do.
I don't know what to do. This is too
much. But I know what not to do.
But I know what not to do.
And that remains. So you just stay
there. But it would be nice if it's clearer
But it would be nice if it's clearer
what I'm supposed to do and if it's more
defined and if this dog just shuts up.
It would be great. And it will be great
if you stay with knowing what not to do,
not with overshooting the mark,
overstepping, and overbeating the dog or
letting it run loose and trying to fear
with that.
That's why in the sutras it's a gradual
training. But it is taming of the elephant like
But it is taming of the elephant like
many sutras talk about it.
And they would provide graphic
descriptions of
the the king sends his his men and they
catch a wild bull elephant, the biggest
one. And then they they drag it and they put
And then they they drag it and they put
big stakes in the ground and tie it
completely confined.
And then it just rages mad, urinates,
defecates, tries to kill everything that
comes near it. And they just stand there
making their presence known. Obviously,
they can't come close cuz it will kill
them. But they can't let it loose cuz well, it
But they can't let it loose cuz well, it
will kill them.
But like they can't just leave it cuz it
will die either. So they have to train
it. But the beginning is confining it. So
But the beginning is confining it. So
the mind will kick and scream cuz you
put boundaries on it.
That's why I said like if you were as I
said, you're bound with the dog. You're
tied with this dog.
And he wants to go left and you go left.
He wants to go right and you go right.
And it feels like it's fine
cuz you haven't tried to stop it.
So you run with it.
And then you don't feel the tension that
it's pulling you because okay, it's all
fine, but the time will come when you
can't You won't run. You can't run.
And then you're going to feel the whole
pull and the pain. And all the training
inadvertently you trained it to run even faster and
you trained it to run even faster and
stronger and quicker. It's going to hurt
even more cuz you made it even wilder to
not recognizing that indirect
responsibility for the dog.
Yes, I wish my dog doesn't bite you.
And I didn't make it bite you.
But I did not train it.
And it is mine and I can't say it's not
mine. So I It's my fault that it bit
you. Just in this case you are the one being
Just in this case you are the one being
bitten as well, so
that's how it works.
What about the Sotapanna? Can he break
Can he break any precept?
Yes. Yeah. He can break all of them.
He can't He can't kill his mother, kill
his father, wound the Buddha,
kill an arahant, violate a Bhikkhuni. He
can't take
any determination activity as permanent.
He can't take any determination as
pleasurable. And he can't regard
anything as his atta, as himself. Those
are the eight things he can't do.
And what would be
um cuz
or you said about that
doubt might be your reason to act Mhm.
Later even. So what would be the
Sotapanna's motivation, the reason to
act the all the precepts
the all the precepts
while breaking the precepts?
Or or being content with knowing the way
out. Or in the standing this game, not
Or in the standing this game, not
suffering
to that great degree.
Yeah, so Sotapanna becomes a Sotapanna
at a certain point by confining and
Yeah, by by understanding what I said,
understanding the right level, and
understanding then where the suffering
comes from because it doesn't come
from the external circumstances. It
doesn't come from external pain or
discomfort or things that you don't
want. It comes from that mind turning
against you.
Because of this or because of that.
That's why sometimes one thing same
thing doesn't make you suffer. On another
doesn't make you suffer. On another
occasion you suffer a lot. Same thing.
So what would be like a difference
in the pull the of this animal for the
Sotapanna and for the Putujana? Well,
yes, but see
a Putujana cannot see that difference
unless he becomes a Sotapanna. Yeah.
That's the only way to find it.
is still still there. Well, no, for for
if you were to compare externally with a
Putujana and Sotapanna next to each
other, you can say yes, there is a
difference. But that's not how it works.
All you have is your individual point of
view. So the pull that you have at the
time is the pull.
Yeah. And if you replace that pull with
Sotapanna's pull Yeah. you won't have
Putujana's pull anymore.
But you can't know the Sotapanna's pull
until you become one.
Yeah, yeah, of course, of course.
So there is no external comparison.
That's exactly why that conceit
disappears in somebody who recognize
this level of the mind and start to
practicing there. The Buddha said, he He
didn't say, "Oh, he abstains from being
proud." He said, "He becomes unable
to think, I am better, I am worse, or I
am equal." Any sense of external
comparison diminishes.
So, from the hindrances, this is only
doubt that would be
uh absent.
No, no.
The doubt is a fetter is absent from his
mind. But, doubt is
But, doubt is
Five hindrances are still there for as
long as he's not an arahant.
You know, they will be weakened and
weakened and weakened, but they will
still arise.
So, I'm I'm I'm curious.
You know, when you talk about the magic
of pain and that it's unpleasant.
Um
Um so, what did
the Buddha mean when he said about these
like four different paths and two of
them are actually
the path to awakening is short and
pleasant or or long and pleasant. Long
and pleasant, short and painful, and
long and painful. When he meant what I'm
describing now, as I said, for somebody
it will feel like dying.
Being confined within these mental
states will be the worst thing. For
somebody it won't.
Because their habits were not as strong,
their craving was not as strong, they
already made the effort in other ways.
But, you you can't decide it. You only
know that in hindsight.
Once you complete the work, you can tell
what way were you.
It's not like, "Oh, I am this type
before you even completed the the the
the work."
But, restraint is never pleasant. So,
how come it's pleasant? It's quite the
opposite. It is pleasant.
It can be pleasant at some point. It's
not pleasant, as I said, cuz but most of
us today
That's our baseline was sensuality
through and through.
But, say there is a beautiful drink, the
best tasting drink in the world.
And you're about to drink it.
And then somebody tells you it has a
poison from the blowfish and you will die
from the blowfish and you will die
within half an hour if you drink it.
And you restrain yourself from drinking
it. Still the same smell, seems still
the same taste, still still the same
consistency. But, the knowledge now
But, the knowledge now
makes you restrain from it. You'll be
the happiest man in the world. You say,
"Wow, I dodged a bullet. I was about to
drink this." And restrained
make this mind feel so happy now cuz it
saved my life.
Same restraint.
Paired with knowledge.
Cuz the things you're restraining
against, by the way, are factually
unpleasant. But, you can't see that cuz you're
But, you can't see that cuz you're
intoxicated with it.
So, you need to restrain until the
intoxication subside and the embers,
exactly. And then it's like, "Oh, no,
this was always painful even when I
enjoyed it."
So, that's the difficult part for me
because the mindset when I start with
this teaching is to kind of prepare
myself for pain, which I guess is a
cleansing itself, but it's unavoidable,
right? Yeah, yeah.
And then when something pleasant occurs,
so when when wholesome qualities occur,
it's like
what do I do with that? And and I often
like notice not often, of course, but
but but it's it feels like there's a kind of
but it's it feels like there's a kind of
like a new approach that is needed,
right? To because also there are these
four efforts and I I also need to know
how to maintain wholesome qualities,
which is quite pleasant, right? But, in
a different way. It's like this
non-sensual way. And I remember you only
once you mentioned that
Well, actually, yes, so some people can
go to this memory of jhana and use it as
a shortcut and go there as a as a like
kind of positive path in a way sometimes
for someone who knows that, right? And
I'm and I'm just wondering why this
asymmetry. Where why why I'm not quite
sure I said it that way, though. Mhm. I
I was I was I was surprised at Yeah, I
don't I maybe maybe came across wrong,
but uh
No, I think that I was referring to what
the Buddha did.
He went to the memory of jhana and then
followed the practice that way cuz he
tried everything else.
That didn't work.
But, most people would there would be no
most people would there would be no
memory of jhana for as long as there is
sensuality as the baseline.
As simple as that. So, memory of jhana
for most people is just a memory of
slightly more loftier sensual
experience. So, that would mean that the only
So, that would mean that the only
wholesome quality that we actively
um kind of maintain is the mindfulness
and mindfulness of the dangers, so to say.
mindfulness of the dangers, so to say.
you don't do.
Mhm. Right. But, but this So, but still
there are these four
four efforts.
Yeah. I'm just wondering
The right effort to not fight the waves,
to not push backwards, and to not stand
still. See, they're all negative types
of effort. But, isn't it the case that
actually wholesome qualities even when
there is just like a spark of them? So,
like Buddhadasa
was was talking, for example, of this
about these wholesome qualities which
occur just in like small amounts What
are those qualities? Sorry? What is I
don't know. Like like like joy, for
example. How do you know it's wholesome?
Is it because joy? I agree. I mean So,
joy in itself it's not necessarily
wholesome. Pain in itself it's not
necessarily unwholesome. That's my
entire point. But, if you use the
feeling of it as the reference,
you're not seeing the middle way. Right.
But, but but uh
right. It feels good. But, doesn't it
isn't it the case that sometimes when
mind sees enough, then it kind of
intuitively feels what's constraining
and what's not the mind? It's like it
feels like growing and does never make
sense to to follow that as a as a
positive reference, so to say, you know?
How would you How would you do How would
you follow it?
Well, okay, maybe that's true. Maybe in
my case the
sometimes I just noticed that the
refinement of not allowing this quality
to grow by itself, you know? Like like
there's this very persistent and
invisible layer of like
being on guard
Okay. which causes maybe
and then it feels like I'm actually Oh,
I can allow this, which feels like I'm
actively going for it. But, maybe it's
not the case. Maybe it's actually just
And this is very subtle and that's why
it's hard for me, right? Well, that's
it. It will stay subtle and that's
obviously why the practice becomes
refined. But, yeah, that is the point.
You're always on guard and then you
recognize, "But, hold on. Like That's
why I gave that ambiguous example where
it's not factually nor morally wrong.
Yet, you would feel guilty.
Because of like, "Well, it's just easier
if it's always like this."
And this comes down to the same. Okay,
so
there is this joy because the mind is
maybe elated because of this. Okay, let
me see where it wants to go. As I was
giving the example this morning,
like taming the animal, whether it's the
elephant or the dog or the cows in other
suttas. Um
Um
You you constrain them
when they go where where they shouldn't.
But, see, when that becomes
develops in the sense of pressuring
duty, it becomes like divorced from that
recognition and then it's just I
restrain them whenever they move.
And that's not going to teach them a
lesson. That's going to confuse them
even more.
The example I was giving, it's like you
hit the cow when it goes to graze where
it shouldn't. Then the cow lay down,
it's about to move, and you hit it. But,
you don't even know why it wanted to
move. Did it want to go into the other
people's property or it just wanted to
stretch and turn around and come back?
And you're not going to find out cuz
you're just beating him now.
So, it's not going to be a clear-cut. You're
it's not going to be a clear-cut. You're
going to be doing it to some extent, but
it's to recognize, "Okay, hold on.
I am not breaking the precept. I am not
giving in to the mental unwholesomeness.
The mind wants to move.
Allow it to move.
See where it goes. If it immediately
runs for the gate,
the dog, okay, you get it back.
If it doesn't, if it's just roaming
around slowly,
let it be.
And that sense of duty, "But, I must.
But, I must." Okay, now that's the
problem. Cuz it's not doing anything wrong. Why
Cuz it's not doing anything wrong. Why
am I correcting it?
And that's how it gets to communicate.
That's how it gets to learn. Aha, look,
he lets me roam around. Only when I step
across, I get pain.
I get pain.
And then it will it will it will bake
itself into its own recognition and then
the mind will obey it.
Cuz you showed it what to do and what
not to do.
This is this probably one of more subtle
aversions uh like kinds of aversion I I
uh like kinds of aversion I I
sometimes I feel aversion. I don't know
what actually to what sense it's pure
towards and then I realize actually it's
not pure towards any of the senses, but
it's pure towards what might appear.
Yeah. So, it's kind of like mental It
might go into the property that doesn't
belong to me, so I better I better deal
with it now.
And that's exactly what I was saying.
No, you need to let those things arise.
That possibility needs to arise and you
need to endure it.
It might go. It gets up. It might go. It
moves. It might go. It might go. Oh,
it's so unpleasant because if it goes
That's the practice.
You hit it not because, "Oh, it might
go." You hit it when it goes.
If it doesn't, you leave it and then you
bear your own irrationality until it
calms down.
I don't know. The other side of the coin
is if I let go of this anxiety,
then I feel what
how freedom may taste because actually
I don't have to do anything at that
point. And I I don't know whether Yeah,
well, see, no, yeah, you cuz you can
then say, "Well, what if I stop worrying
about other people's fields? There will
be nothing, then I'll be at peace."
But, you should stop worrying about
other people's fields only when you're
fully enlightened and there is no more
But, like to small extent, I mean. Like
like Again, to small extent, you
shouldn't stop worrying about
possibility. But, you should stop beating the animal
But, you should stop beating the animal
if it's not going there because of that
possibility that it might.
And that's the middle ground, I see. Cuz
I say, "Okay, no. Let the animal" People
will mean, "Okay, so I can drop the
worrying." No, no, no, no. I didn't say
that. You won't You need to worry on the right
You won't You need to worry on the right
level.
But, not choke the animal as a result of
it.
I think the sense just that there is
expansion of the mind. So there is more
freedom like There will be, yeah.
I mean that's even what the how the
simile goes.
The cows roam in other people's crop. If
he doesn't do he get punished, he'll get
beaten, he'll get put in jail, he'll pay
the price to find.
So he's really worried and constantly
keeps them back and hits them and ropes
them and everything. But then he
recognizes they're wandering less and
less and then they stop wandering.
And then they are just staying here and
then he goes to sleep.
Wakes up, cows are still there, haven't
haven't haven't left.
No problem.
Cuz he did work
through rightly directed boring.
And that's again that won't be visible
if somebody still has a view
that well I must deal with this. I must
get rid of this worry. I must get rid of
this. Not not necessarily.
Maybe I can just
one more and then stop and then I asked
before what is the difference between
doubt hindrance and doubt feather?
And why is doubt? Sorry to interrupt but
I I was thinking why is doubt? Sometimes
there is like a wise doubt, right? Wise
doubt? Wise wise. A wise doubt.
Well that wouldn't be a doubt. It
wouldn't be a doubt in this sense. It
wouldn't be constraining you one way or
the other. It wouldn't be pressuring
you. You'd be like wisely deflecting and
questioning. But so what do you think?
But so what do you think?
What what what what would you think if I
asked you what would be the difference?
Just whatever comes to mind.
Between a doubt Say say it's the same
doubt.
But one fetters you
One person's fettered by that doubt.
Another one is just hindered but not
fettered. I guess that was then the basic question
I guess that was then the basic question
what's the difference between hindrances
and fetters.
That's pretty much it.
So which one do you think it's more
fundamental? Fetters? Fetters are is
more more fundamental. Exactly not.
Not? It's hindrances. Hindrances.
Hindrances Fetters are the result of
untamed hindrances.
Mhm. That's why they would start falling off
That's why they would start falling off
the closer to arahantship you get. Mhm.
And that's why the arahant is the
destroyer of the hindrances.
So it's this individual giving ins to
sensuality, ill will, restlessness, worry, anxiety,
ill will, restlessness, worry, anxiety,
doubt. That's what feeds the fetters.
That's what provides fuel for them and
thus they fetter you in return.
So really the difference between fetters
and the like say the first three fetters
that fall off in a sotapanna it's
because he has already been training
rightly in regard to the five
hindrances. He's not blindly irrationally trying to
He's not blindly irrationally trying to
get rid of them.
He's not psychologizing them. He's not
managing them.
He allowed them to arise on the right
level and learn how to see through them
through not acting out of them.
That's that sutta that I often quote cuz
what people think oh so just bear it
just bear it. It's like no the sutta is
quite clear. You have perceptions of
sensuality present themselves. That's
not a hindrance.
Wrongly attending to it, picking it up,
that's now a hindrance. That's why it's
a hindrance.
And then the word in the same sutta
describes how he freed. Not oh then he
thinks about this and does that then he
becomes from the right he moves to the
left. No he says he stops attending to
them wrongly while the thing remains.
And that's how you train in regard to
the hindrances.
You do that sufficiently
the extent of the fetters will diminish.
In other words say you start taking the
right medicine not perfectly but more
and more accurately and some of the
coarser symptoms of your illness just
disappear. They are cured.
They are cured.
They fall off. So
So
like in that case when there is still
hindrance of of doubt
in sotapanna
but there is no feather of doubt.
Yeah. But for example the next next
two fetters are
the the fourth fetter is chandaraga.
So
it would be for anagami. He gets rid of
that. And
And
but there still would be the hindrance
of sensual desire. For whom? For
anagami. But no. No? No.
But no. No? No.
Hindrance chandaraga it's a sensuality
that's gone. Because that's the fetter.
Oh sorry you meant the hindrance of
sensuality. Yeah yeah I suppose.
The hindrance of sensuality. Yeah yeah
it would be there but it won't be the
central hindrance.
It would for him it would be exemplified
through that craving for being
and craving for non-being what the
suttas describe.
See it's the extent of the hindrance
that determines the the size of the
fetter. Mhm. So the size of sexual desire and
Mhm. So the size of sexual desire and
anger and ill will it's gone in an
anagami. But that which used to be wrongly
But that which used to be wrongly
attended that was resulting in
sensuality and anger is now the
craving for non-being, craving for
being. And that still hinders him to the extent
And that still hinders him to the extent
that he wrongly attends to it.
And then if he stops doing that then all
the 10 hindrances are gone.
Sorry the 10 fetters and all the five
hindrances are destroyed. Yeah. So
according to that it would for a
sotapanna it would be hindrance of doubt
and the and the feather of doubt.
Then he would
like there would be certain things
there would be certain things
for puthujjana for which sotapanna
wouldn't have any more doubt.
Uh
Is it not the case? Well uh
if you're comparing them as I said
before when you asked about difference
between the pressures
it would be maybe correct in theory if
you put them side by side but from your
point of view you can never see that
way. So if you're not a sotapanna whatever
So if you're not a sotapanna whatever
you're doubtful
is your fetter as well.
Cuz you're not training your mind in
regard to the phenomenon of doubt.
The more you train your mind in the
phenomenon regard to phenomenon of doubt
you'll be less and less doubtful.
And when you're a sotapanna then
whatever is doubtful there it won't be
fettering you. It will be hindering you.
But the practice of dealing with it
was always the same cuz you what you're
dealing with is not the fetters.
You're dealing with hindrances whether
you're a puthujjana or an arahant. Well
arahant wouldn't. Leading up to an
arahant. So fetters are the extent of the
So fetters are the extent of the
symptoms.
So they offer you
a measure
of where you are at while the practice
of rightly attending, not giving in,
enduring on the right level remains
unchanged. So that's what I mean in a way it
So that's what I mean in a way it
doesn't matter
to figure out the difference cuz the
work is the same and to actually figure
out the difference you just need to do
that same work.
But it can be helpful obviously
to people with certain maybe
affinities and characteristics and ways
of thinking. That's why the Buddha did
talk about
that much. He talked about fetters
because they were constantly asking him
about rebirth and stuff. Oh this. He
says well let me give you a general
guideline. So if it's like these three
symptoms are gone it's about like this.
If these five symptoms it's more like
this. It wasn't necessarily to like oh one
It wasn't necessarily to like oh one
fetter, two, three. Oh I felt the third
one fall off and stuff like that.
It's training in regard to the five
ways your mind will try to get you.
Every every worry, every suffering that
you have will boil down to one of the
hindrances. It has to. There is no
nothing in between.
Doubt is going to be based on desire,
ill will, restlessness, anxiety, or
doubt. Or that laziness and distraction.
Those are the five ways it tries to like
get you to act,
trick you, trap you.
So are there any reasons to pick either
these as a as a guidelines or three
fetters?
The both different times. Whatever
inspires you to do the right effort on
the right level.
Specifically about sloth and torpor and
this kind of
one of these hindrances. How
because when when it comes to restlessness
when when it comes to restlessness
restlessness it it's kind of more
intuitive what to Mhm. how to endure
that. Mhm.
To not for example start doing things
left and right. And when it comes to
sloth and torpor it is more like no now
I'm going to stand up and do things to
not be Right right right. But in some
sense aversion to sloth and torpor.
Yeah. Yeah so if again it depends on the it's
Yeah so if again it depends on the it's
not always going to be the same sloth
and torpor like if
if it's just drowsy and it's just
constantly you're drifting away then
yeah get up wake yourself up in that
sense. But it's more like
But it's more like
when that pressure to like lay down,
sleep, or not want to I don't want to
think about my intentions now.
That's the important one to recognize.
If like oh I'm sleepy well go to sleep.
Maybe you are tired.
And then you wake up and don't want to
get up but want to continue laying down.
Well now you know it's laziness.
Then get up.
If you don't want to think about things
that are unpleasant related to practice
well you recognize well okay.
That's clearly clearly because I don't
want to deal with it. I'm I'm I'm lazy.
On that level where it matters. Doesn't
mean I shouldn't be lazy and go and
start doing random projects.
But when it comes to not tolerating
these unwholesome states, they try to
pressure you to accept them, act out of
them, you're never lazy there. There is
never a rest there.
On that on that mental level where your
intentions where your choices are, where
the gate is.
Where you open and close
the entrance to the secret.
You can't. You can't afford it.
But as I said, initially it might feel
like I have to watch this all the time,
but as we described, actually it's not
like you have an intention and you know
that it's there and you don't need to
police it.
You don't need to chase the thoughts
that come out of it or go in.
You just need to not lose the sight that
when that
time to choose comes.
That's important.
And that's actually quite effortless.
Like there's that similar I I don't
remember where I read it.
I think it was in the sutras, but I
might have come up with it. I don't
really know. It was the swing.
The children on a swing.
So you have your child on a swing and
you could run with the swing constantly
trying to
look at the child or you could step back
from which you see both ends of the
swing and make sure that it stays within
the normal range.
Or like you have to look after 20
children or something.
You could individually chase one by one
and you won't last long.
Or you could you know go up climb up and
then from which you see them all and
when they then you bring them back.
So this is the same when it comes to
intention intentions. Initially it feels
like I have to police every millisecond
of my life, but that's not what
intentions are.
Intentions are in the back of your mind
and you're already deciding. You're
already choosing and you're not you're
ignoring that cuz you're looking in the
wrong place.
The gateway is you know
It's it's the only thing you need
really. Mhm.
Mhm.
I have a question about this gray line
maybe between the maintaining
between the maintaining
the the suffering and the potentially
kind of like wise you know Patanjali
maybe practices to
to make some things more apparent. So so
as an example
um
if I let's say I wake up and I know I
have like eight hours in in front of
computer talking to a lot of people
and I feel the you know some very kind
of subtle but pervasive feeling, right?
And what what I could do is
if I start working, I won't be able
because I have to still manage the
conversation, I won't be able to
wholesomely like wholesome in a
wholesome way kind of deal with it, but
I could do yoga which
makes it more prominent the feeling and
it's unpleasant, right? So I'm doing it.
You could say that I'm doing it to get
rid of it, but also you could say I'm
doing it to
be able to deal with it
kind of face to face and also in in a
situation where I actually can, right?
So
so so I'm wondering like where where's
the line. It depends on your intention.
You just answered it. If you're doing it
to get rid of it, well
you're acting wrongly.
But if you're doing it to highlight it,
that's fine.
Cuz you will be doing the work of
enduring
Yeah, and this is unpleasant because
there's doubt of course.
So because we we had this car
conversation when when we were coming
here. So
on that
kind of perspective
couldn't it be said that also like good
old nostril breathing or I knew you were
going to go there. pranayama. I'm not
doing it, but I mean No, I know that
your question would go there. But you
know but exactly there are situations
where with the right intention you could
use it to for example I have I don't
have a lot of time and you know we are
living busy lives unfortunately moreover
and then I can go to the this is one of
the most extreme and kind of um
clear examples of
restraint because I give it very
specific focus, right? And then it's clear and
focus, right? And then it's clear and
then there's more effort to be done, but
it's more so to say pronounced so it's
more effective in a way, right? Yeah,
well first it's not restraint though.
Well Restraint is about not doing what's
Restraint is about not doing what's
there wanting to be done. Sorry, let me
let me explain. So so the idea is I
I sit down, close my eyes, I am with the
the state because I know that then it's
going to be most obvious that it wants
to go somewhere else, right?
Assuming it's the case because it's like
Yeah, yeah, okay. Okay, but then why are
you not letting it go somewhere else?
As as I said, why is the movement bad
you say? I mean I would agree with you.
So I was kind of playing with you. See,
that's why generically I always
criticize these meditations cuz
generically they are always rooted in
the same.
Having said that, having said that, I
said in many talks, yes, of course, if
it's too much, I can't just I'm just
overwhelmed and tired. I have to manage
so many things, sit down and calm down,
relax. Do the yoga, do whatever to calm down,
Do the yoga, do whatever to calm down,
but don't confuse that for the practice
cuz it's not. But but sometimes you you
describe it as just sitting down and not
doing anything else and focusing on not
doing anything else If that's what you
want to do, that's also fine. If you
want to watch your belly move and cuz
that's what calms you down, that's also
fine. But
But
actually I I think it's there is
something else in between. So so you you
sometimes mention like just sitting not
not also indulging in a meditation
technique Okay. right? But but but only
saying to myself I won't I won't do
anything else so negatively describing
that. And that would be would you agree
proper practice? Well, that would be
less wrong practice.
It can still be rooted in wrong things,
but you're not going to do it perfectly
for the right reasons all the time from
the start. But yes, see that practice
prevents you from cuz see when you say
I'm focusing, you have restraint, you
don't. Restraint is where intentions
are. Focusing shuts down
Focusing shuts down
the intentions. Like say there is a cow
that wants to go I'm not letting it. Let
me focus on this where I stop seeing the
cow and I get peaceful.
That's not restraint.
Now as I said, if sometimes you do that
cuz you just can't handle cows or dogs
anymore, you've had enough.
Of course, you're going to do it. But if
you now think that that's the practice,
you are just even worse than than before
you started meditating.
Although you might feel more peaceful
because you're ignoring the problem of a
wild animal.
That's why inevitably
all such meditations share the common
view of thoughts and thinking is bad and
I must stop it and focus away and
concentrate away from it.
But that was never the problem. And
same, you inadvertently described how
no, when it wants to move I restrain it,
but why?
Because by doing that you start to imply
that movement is bad.
He mustn't move.
Move, no, stop, get back. Why?
Did it go somewhere it shouldn't? Well,
I don't know cuz I didn't even let it
tell me.
Right because the practice you described
which is just sitting down, it's not
about restraining the body but
restraining the impulses to move to do
something else. See them come up.
to do this. Let them come up and then
recognize your responsibility in
accepting them, delighting what the
sutras say and acting out of them.
But not prevent them from coming up cuz
they're uncomfortable when they're
present.
But isn't like
this neutral object, right? So
isn't it a way also to see it coming? So
because sometimes I'm so you know one
can be so again immersed in thinking
that it's it's hard to even notice that
it's happening. right? Like to what
extent is it
What? See what coming?
The some The unwholesome impulses or
some The unwholesome impulses or
something. unwholesome impulses. Yeah.
So well, let me give you
an experiment example and see which one
have really helps.
Say you never heard about sense
restraint. And nobody ever told you the value of
And nobody ever told you the value of
not acting out on the impulses.
And all you heard was about relaxing
through the breathing.
Would it even occur to you on account of
that practice
to say no to these impulses and to start
seeing danger in them and not give in to
them and regard them as dirt and pain
and boil like the sutras describe? You
wouldn't. You would not in a million years of
You would not in a million years of
meditation techniques cuz it doesn't
lead to that.
Consequently, for the sake of the
experiment, you never heard about
meditation techniques.
Never did any.
But you were told sensual impulses are
bad. Try and contain them in your mind,
remind yourself of it, don't forget
about them.
How would you remind yourself now? How
would you help your reminding of it when
you never heard a meditation technique?
It doesn't really relate to it.
You would do it by remembering what you
already learned, by learning more, by
discerning more danger in them. That's
why the Buddha said, one is not free
from sensuality not because they haven't
practiced meditation hard enough.
It's because they haven't understood the
danger of giving in hard enough.
They haven't discerned the poison.
They still think sometimes it's not
poisonous. And no matter concentration thing will
And no matter concentration thing will
make you catch the poison
if you don't fully understand it.
And that's not on the level of
concentration.
In other words, what you are
concentrating has nothing to do with it.
And that whole idea of concentration
helps you catch the moments. Moments are
the result
of your restraint or non-restraint. It's
not where choice to restrain or
non-restrain comes from.
I I I fully agree with that, but
sometimes I'm talking about these
activities which are going on,
let's say it feels like, you know,
months at a time, all the time, and it's
so hard to notice it. So, for example,
sometimes some mental attitudes, like being in a
some mental attitudes, like being in a
So, it's correlates, for example, with
being some part of the body and not the
other part of the body. Like emotional.
But why is that a problem?
Why is it something you need to notice?
Mhm. Because I notice that when it's gone,
Because I notice that when it's gone,
then it like the mind is more open. It
it's like it there is there is some kind
of attachment, but it's so subtle that I
cannot So, in other words, you're saying
when the discomfort is gone, it feels
nice. Mhm.
And you're back where you started. So,
it's not the the right level, you know,
what I mean.
Well, exactly. I'm saying you're still
and you would be if you think that
through concentration you'll be catching
these differences, means you're still
guided by how you feel. As in uh
uncomfortable, I need to address this.
It's at the back of my mind for 3
months. Well,
is it a problem just because it's
uncomfortable? Does that make it a
problem? Not necessarily, as we just
described earlier on.
It might be, but then it's not because
of the reasons because it's
uncomfortable. Until I see this thing, this tension as
Until I see this thing, this tension as
presented as my current choice, which
usually comes with practice
your current choice, the most current
choice there and then, it's are you
choosing to
habitually, blindly,
want to get rid of the discomfort?
Are you implying habitually, blindly,
that presence of discomfort is bad?
And you realize
that's not a justified position.
Because why is it bad?
Because it's unpleasant. That's not a
That That should not be the the
baseline. That should not be a reference
point. Yet, it is. That's the nature of
craving. The craving for more pleasure in
The craving for more pleasure in
pleasure pleasurable feeling, craving
for less pain in in in unpleasant
feeling. It's the fundamental attitude. Approve
It's the fundamental attitude. Approve
that attitude, you're free from
suffering. You're in nirvana completely.
That's why I say often, "It doesn't
matter why this happened. Why did I do
this?" Cuz there and then all of those
movements would be rooted in
it's unpleasant and I don't want it and
I'm doing anything I can to get rid of
it.
So, it would be the same. Concentration
helps me catch
where suffering isn't.
The suffering is not in those things
that you catch, in those subtle
perceptions. Suffering is in your
persisting attitude
of leaning away from it, wanting it to
go away.
And no amount of concentration will show
you that because
any effort of concentration is rooted in
that attitude. It's done for that very
reason.
It's scary for people to accept. That's
why they often irrationally try to
refute it, but they can't.
So, it's always like
yeah, but I find it helpful.
Yeah, I don't know, but but I I it
helped me a lot with this or helped me a
lot with that. And the reason why it's
scary is because it leave it seemingly
leaves you
like without any attempt at escape.
It fully reveals the confinement
of your mind.
See, if you give up
a little attempt at just management and
lessening of this, you're just left
fully confined. There is no outside of
this which is now at the moment painful.
And that's, by the way, how you free
yourself from atman vada as well.
It's not in incidental that
understanding these things would drop
off the three fetters.
The whole
uh
premise, the whole uh phenomenon behind
atman vada is implying
the self
independent I external to this
experience as a whole.
In other words, magically believing in
way out
because if there is no way out, even
mundane things would be unbearable.
But see, they're unbearable not because
there is no way out.
They're unbearable because you crave
against not having the way out.
If you stop craving, then the
confinement, as the sutra say, become
the opening.
That which was confining you is actually
what the freedom is.
The impermanence is actually what frees
you from burden.
The fact that you can't own things even
if you want to.
But for that, you need to confine
yourself first.
And there's actually a sutra um
that uh
I think it was like a uh a monk.
It wasn't the Buddha.
And he was talking to a king's
charioteer. And the the king's charioteer said, "Oh,
And the the king's charioteer said, "Oh,
I heard
that your teacher, he teaches about
you know, freedom like from confinement,
openings amidst the confinement."
And then he asked him like, "Yes, but
what do you understand by confinement?"
I'm paraphrasing. And he said, "Well,
let me give you an example. He's a
charioteer, and sometimes the king
orders him to take his wives riding on
horses. So, he would sit on a horse with one
So, he would sit on a horse with one
wife in front and one in the back.
And they're all dressed up and perfumed,
and he knows
that even if he just accidentally
touches them, he'll he'll chop his head
off, the king.
So, he's fully confined with this, and
any direction of movement
is going to be the end of him.
But that's his job, basically.
And then he says, "Yeah, that would be
one confinement." And obviously
corresponds as an example,
but the confinement that the Buddha
teaches freedom from, it's even greater
than that. Mhm. Mhm.
And that's the whole freedom from atman
vada that it's going to feel very
confined, claustrophobic, closed.
Cuz there is no outside movement that
wouldn't fall within the movement. There
is no outside action or choice that
wouldn't fall within the internal
intention of action. So, there is no
outside of it. Now, you can say to
yourself, "Okay, there's no outside of
it." And still imply the outside. You truly
And still imply the outside. You truly
train train yourself within that
confinement by not giving into this
management that I talk about, or trying
to get rid of it, and look for the
problem where it isn't.
That will confine you. That will feel
uncomfortable to the extent that you
resist it.
And that's usually why people like
feels like too much to ask if you tell
them your meditation is
as I said, 99.9% is going to be rooted
in wrong reasons and be taking you away
from the direction where you should be
going. As I said, yes, there can always be an
As I said, yes, there can always be an
exception to a rule where somebody does
genuinely cuz
physically they're exhausted or this,
and they just want to wind down, not do
anything, and they don't do it for that
reason. But more often than not, that
will be the reason.
And we come back to what we said. So,
why is the confinement bad? Why is that
so scary?
I mean, you're just confined within
yourself. Why is that the worst possible thing?
Why is that the worst possible thing?
Why do you need others, external
distractions, actions, desires?
It's like, "Oh, actually, yeah. It's a
good question that I don't know the
answer to."
And the answer is not some great
philosophical mystery. It's because you
habitually don't know how to not lean
towards pleasure,
habitually lean uh immediately away from
pain. And if it's neither pleasure nor pain,
And if it's neither pleasure nor pain,
you don't know how to just go into
oblivion. Cuz enduring those things on those
Cuz enduring those things on those
emotional levels, it's the most
uncomfortable.
Is that a particular layer?
It's not too much
when it's just coarsely overwhelming you
that you can get used to, actually.
And it's not too little where it's just
invisible. It's just there at the back of your mind
It's just there at the back of your mind
all the time, day in, day out, seemingly
preventing you to find happiness in the
world cuz it is always there. It's like,
"Well, exactly."
Cuz the possibility of cessation,
impermanence, it's always there.
So, what you are having there
inadvertently is how things actually
are, and it's not going to feel
pleasant.
I guess it's not even just the the skill
of like how to be exactly in the middle,
No. but not even having the view that
these are just pleasant and unpleasant
thing because I have a which is so
incomparable. It's like different
universe, right? Yeah.
Yeah, the view is the like the leading
constraint. Yeah, the view basically
takes you in the either right direction
or bad direction, depending on it.
That's why it's important to clarify,
but you can spend lifetime just clarifying
you can spend lifetime just clarifying
things if you don't actually start doing
it on the right level that matters, and
doing it on the right level, like I keep
saying, it's it's not it's not going to it's not
it's it's not it's not going to it's not
going to develop.
And sometimes feel it just feels too
much. Is it, though?
Is life the way it is, is it not too
much? With all the implications and stress
With all the implications and stress
and burden, ever-increasing burden. It's
not a static thing. Ever-increasing What
is that Is that Is that okay? Well,
even the great people that would say,
"Yes, it is." It's only cuz at the
moment they're able to run with that
wild dog. Deep down, they know that it
won't last forever. They will have to
stop. And when they do then that dog will
And when they do then that dog will
probably tear them apart cuz he became
so wild by that point and they became so
weak that there will be nothing they can do
that there will be nothing they can do
about it.
That's the the whole like simile of
aging is coming, sickness is coming,
death is coming, unavoidable.
So, either way
whether you choose to ignore this
and just fully enjoy the life like there
is no tomorrow
heading the same way.
So, you might as well try at least do
something about it.
And how could that the people in the
sutta develop in the right direction
develop in the right direction
even before talking to the Buddha? Like
because this
one one one point becomes up. Well,
think about it this like today take an
average person
generally even the underprivileged or
whatever else wouldn't be worrying
about their immediate life or existence
of food whether or not they'll be
tomorrow and stuff. You know, it comes
and goes but it's no but back then that
was the reality. Yeah. So, they could
not become as complacent as we are
today. And that's exactly how the mind became
And that's exactly how the mind became
developed.
These things were at the back of their
mind whether they wanted them or not.
Not everybody like it's not a guarantee
that you're going to develop but if it's
there with rightly attending to it,
recognizing it then the the wisdom can
take place.
And that's exactly what some people like
just needed to hear about the Buddha and
what he told to somebody else
and it was enough for them to understand
cuz they already had everything there to
be seen.
They just needed the actual aha.
Yeah, so yeah, exactly.
This was something I was wondering
wondering recently that more than the
difference in sensuality because it's
easy to imagine that the problem in
modern age is sensuality because we have
much more entertainment, much more
exciting food, and much more
stimulation. But maybe it's not so much the problem
But maybe it's not so much the problem
in sensuality because even back then
they had music, singing, and sex and all
that. It's more the
It's more the
the how much we take for granted
physical safety and how much we take for
granted comfort
dying in in a late age Yeah. We we all
imagine that we would only live at least
at 50, 70. Yeah. But it's it's just a
gratuitous. Yeah. Yeah, very much so.
Exactly. Yeah, people have got softer basically.
Yeah, people have got softer basically.
Isn't it also about the not just lack of
the teaching but also anti-teaching of
alternative religions of like marketing?
So, so seeing not just being
uh not just being kind of, you know,
having those pleasures but also having
the sense of
identity still cultivated by
still cultivated by
by actual lot of effort, you know, from
the outside world to to have this
uh you know, self of worth identified
with being that or the Yeah, but all
that's done because people want safety.
People assume safety in it.
You know, when you see somebody it
offers you some some sense of comfort.
When you get respect it offers you sense
of comfort, pleasure.
It does boil down to the very basic
cravings. Never leaves that level.
Yes, it can be more sugar like like then
condensed in it but it's always going to
be that same universally motivating
factor. That's why
the teaching, the freedom from it that
the Buddha student that he taught he
said it's a universal principle. Doesn't
matter the the gender, age, culture
every mind works along these principles
of craving against pain, craving towards
pleasure, and craving towards ignorance
when it's neither pleasure nor pain.
oblivion, distraction
If the intention is to
save the pain of the dying animal, then
it's right.
You're killing it.
Yeah, but if the dying animal
Yeah, but killing it hurts as well. So
what pain are you saving?
your pain
of watching the pain of an animal.
It's going to die anyway.
So, why are you rushing it?
So, you think it's not right
It's not right. Killing it's never
right.
Cuz you you you you are not privy to its
perspective.
And although it seems like yeah, it's
painful and so on, what makes you think
that death is not worse pain than that?
So, you would be acting out of your own
desire by doing it.
But the culture is becoming like that.
That you know Oh, yeah. Oh, yeah. Like
what kind of a dog owner are you Yeah,
yeah, of course. to let the dog
die naturally then
instead of going to sleep with the you
know, even and it's like
old and cold the same like
or sit there and suffer. So, the dog is
not really even dying. You're not
killing the dog. You're putting the dog
to sleep.
Just to excuse
already rightly
Well, same like what's done with
abortion as well. Mhm. You rebrand it.
Yeah. Don't call it for what it is.
Yeah. And then it becomes perfectly
acceptable in few generations time. It
becomes a norm.
People will say well, it's not alive.
Like what I just killed.
It's yeah, it's that's exactly the
collective avoidance of responsibility.
That's how it works.
Because we have a basically the idea
that with death
we put an end, you know put an end to
its suffering. Yeah, we we Yeah. We we
don't we don't uh
kind of even uh
have a little put a doubt on this idea.
Yeah, but hold on. Do I know it's the
end? Exactly.
Do I know it's not even worse?
It won't be able to tell you by the way.
But yeah.
So, you realize you have no reference.
You're claiming like you're believing
oh, it's a but you have no reference for
where that animal is.
Or a person. You're doing it for
yourself. One way or the other.
It has to be coming out of your desire.
Even if it's like a noble desire
it's still going to be your desire from
your limited perspective.
And in this case
it's ending of someone else's life on
account of your limited perspective. So,
it's like
probably better to avoid it.
What is your um what is your um
recommendation for
practice for lady? What reason?
What reason?
Depends how far you want to go.
In terms of the practice?
Daily practice like No, no, how far you
want to go in terms of the results.
What do you want to achieve? Well,
depends how much you have to start
giving up.
If you don't want to keep more than five
precepts, then you have to lower your
expectations. And work a lot harder in other areas.
And work a lot harder in other areas.
So, it won't be the most efficient
practice. Yeah, that's So, then you ask yourself
Yeah, that's So, then you ask yourself
so, hold on. I'm already in an
unsuitable environment. household life
bombarded with stuff
many duties
and I'm taking
a non-efficient approach.
Mhm. Exactly but So what is the
likelihood of success?
You don't know but you can guess that
it's probably lower.
So, then you have to be
well, you have to recognize that and not
kind of believe that
no, no, no, I'm still practicing for the
final liberation. No, no, no, not at
all. While you're refusing to obtain
lower expectations. Yeah, well, how far
you go is how far you apply yourself.
But yeah, theoretically you can
get some sense of freedom and some
insights if you're really clear and and do things
if you're really clear and and do things
on the higher level.
Not just blindly adhere to prescribed
methods instructions.
This kind of the question
That's the practice.
As I said, you can't know how far you go
before you start before you reach it.
If you take more than five precepts, you
have a better chance of succeeding.
Even with lesser amount of effort. So So
factor in
the time factor, how much time you have
left the health factor
the health factor
the circumstances factor and then see
whether you can afford a slow
uncompromised, non-efficient approach or not.